<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: difficult second version | Devops malarkey]]></title>
  <link href="http://failcake.github.com/blog/categories/difficult-second-version/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://failcake.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-10-14T22:31:33+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://failcake.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bodge and Guesswork]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finding places to put things]]></title>
    <link href="http://failcake.github.com/blog/2012/12/28/finding-places-to-put-things/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-28T23:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://failcake.github.com/blog/2012/12/28/finding-places-to-put-things</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I suspect this blog-thing will just contain sporadic apologies for lack of content for most of its lifetime.</p>

<p>Anyway.</p>

<p>This time the excuses have been brought to you by the words 'fail', 'power', 'generator', 'contactor', '250A supply',
'melted' and the phrases 'boot that filer from a different Vol0', 'can you smell smoke?' and 'Oh hell not again'.</p>

<p>As you might imagine, it's been busy and the DR plan has been tested and found interesting.</p>

<p>We're still Barberising and Hiera-ing up our shonky collection of Puppet modules. I'd say that they're getting less
shonky by the day, but it's taking longer than that. I hesitate to talk about 'patterns', because... Actually, I think
that's an example of self-taught-hacker anti-intellectualism, which is an equal amount of rubbish as its opposite.</p>

<p>So. The Barberis(ing|ed) pattern is a fine thing and, when used in combination with the wonder that is Hiera, allows us
to do more things in simpler code.</p>

<p>However. One of the modules that I'd been putting off refactoring (so 'patterns' are suspect but 'refactoring' is fine,
eh?) was the one that manages our NSD install and thus the DNS for quite a number of domains, some of which contain
rather popular websites.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.nlnetlabs.nl/projects/nsd/">NSD is the authoritative-only nameserver daemon written by NLNet Labs</a>, who are a top bunch of chaps. We abandoned Bind
after there were one too many vulnerability notices.</p>

<p>I'd been putting off the work because the v0.1 module just drops the entirety of the zone-files directory under
../files/ and lets Puppet do the work of synchronising the files across the nameservers. It's not as if it's a terrible
thing to do at first glance - Puppet's file-serving means you can stop faffing with hand-brewed rsync scripts for
managing the out-of-band DNS data, and if you've got your Puppet tree in a sensible SCM, you get version control 'for
free'.</p>

<p>However (again), great lumps of org-specific data like that shouldn't really, we are told, be held within the module
tree. It's not necessarily obvious where the data should go, though. Nor is it terribly obvious how you connect it back
to the Puppet module and have changes in the one signal the other to perform tasks.</p>

<p>Well, it is if you look at the right corners of the Internet, but this thing is mostly me groping around and trying
stuff out as a warning to others.</p>

<p>NSD installation and management goes in the now-Barberised NSD module.</p>

<p>This also deposits code that rebuilds the NSD config file when a domain is added or removed. And indeed the out-of-band
master list of domains, which semi-obviously has to travel separately from the zonefiles for $reasons.</p>

<p>(It's about this time that someone-who-is-not-me would be going 'Why isn't all this domain gubbins in a nice database
somewhere, then all zone maintenance would be a simple 'SELECT mumble FROM yinglebart WHERE tewkesbury ISNT something'',
which would be very shortly before I hauled out the sarcasm throwing machine.)</p>

<p>The zonefiles live in a git repo of their own. That repo is cloned down onto the master DNS server(s) and kept current via the
magic of post-commit hooks. Meanwhile, there's a file resource in the NSD module which looks like this:</p>

<pre><code>file { '/var/lib/nsd3/.git/HEAD':
  audit   =&gt; content,
  notify  =&gt; Exec['rebuild'],
}

exec { 'rebuild':
  command     =&gt; '/etc/nsd3/code/refresh.sh',
  refreshonly =&gt; true,
}
</code></pre>

<p>... Which is lifted wholesale from
<a href="https://github.com/jordansissel/puppet-examples/tree/master/unmanaged-file-notify">here.</a> Either we've found one of the non-terrible use cases for this hack, or I'll be
writing another rambling post in a few months when I've had a better idea.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leveraged neatness is not always your friend]]></title>
    <link href="http://failcake.github.com/blog/2012/09/11/leveraged-ocd-is-not-always-your-friend/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-11T15:19:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://failcake.github.com/blog/2012/09/11/leveraged-ocd-is-not-always-your-friend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I must begin by apologising for using the word 'leveraged'. It's terrible
 marketing-speak. However, it mostly fits in context and anyway I am using
 it in an ironic sense. (not that that's even a valid excuse for the likes
 of me, but there you go.)</p>

<p>There are certain aspects of the admin trades where semi-obsessive neatness
and/or attention to detail are useful things to have. It's one of the times
where not being able to leave the house without checking that you've turned the
gas off twice and locked the front door three times can be a positive thing to
admit in an interview. [NB: Self-deprecating hyperbole.]</p>

<p>It can also lead to the sort of unfortunate failure-modes that if you're lucky
you're not familiar with.</p>

<p>(This was all kicked off by one of the network guys asking me some hard
questions about the nature of packaging and dependencies, which set me off on a
bit of a ramble. Thus network types get it first. Beard-fondling admins get
their kicking later.)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Twice now, I've been in jobs where the greater part of the network has been
rebuilt. If you imagine <em>everything</em> being lifted up while new wires are
plumbed in by a selection of blokes with disturbing arsecracks, then you'd not
be far wrong. Towards the end of the work, the relevant network manager has
(metaphorically) straightened up, dusted off their hands and declared the task
complete. And then the terrible oiks in charge of the servers have started
migrating services to the shiny new bits of wire, to discover that only about a
third of the routes are in place and next to none of the odd ports required to
make the databases work or sodding undocumented OSX distributed p/w malarkey.
Thus there's a sudden pile of change-requests (or an aggrieved queue next to
the network manager's cube) followed by quite a lot of grousing about 'making
my nice clean network diagram all complicated with your filthy packets and
honestly why are you people even <em>using</em> Oracle?'</p>

<p>Which, um, yes.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, there used to be one of those Rules of Thumb that became
over-generalised by people who were massively missing the point on purpose. It
went along the lines of 'the process-list on your unix box should only be about
a screen long, and if you don't <em>know</em> what the various jobs are doing and
which ports they're using, disable them.</p>

<p>That's actually sensible behaviour if you're talking about some hateful SysV
box that's acting as a firewall or bastion host back in the old days when
Solaris was a relevant OS (Pre Y2K) and everything came with inetd enabled with
the tiresome daemons that no-one understood. (ticotsord? Daft name for anything
that's not a planet in a space-trading MMO.)</p>

<p>However, it's only going to make everyone else hate you if you drag that
attitude along into the world of Linux distros and try to out-stubborn the
package-manager. Don't do that. I know that sinking feeling when I see the
resulting trail of gubbins that gets hauled in like tin cans on string
following the bride &amp; groom's car in a Carry-on film when I type 'apt-get
install default-jre', and I have learned to let it go.</p>

<p>Not letting that sort of thing go ends in something like 'And that, your
honour, is when I decided to create my own Linux distribution...'</p>

<p>It happens in tool-building, too. One of the things I half-promised myself was
that the stomp-git daemon would never do anything careless with the
repositories. All it would do is a 'git fetch' and anything further would be
under the control of a carbon-unit. That was a splendid plan until I discovered
that actually I needed the thing to keep a Puppetmaster tree in sync behind a
firewall. Well, ok. That's a special mode which requires a specific
command-line option which is well documented in the config file and the
initscript.</p>

<p>Then I needed to keep a hieradata tree in sync across two puppetmasters, and an
(this!) Octopress install working, and it turned out that some rearranging of
the config file made the code less worse and the ease of doing dangerous thing
more better.</p>

<p>I'm not sure how I feel about that. It's made several things really quite
trivial, but it really doesn't sit well with me.</p>

<p>Funny business, code.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In which there is silence and excuses for same]]></title>
    <link href="http://failcake.github.com/blog/2012/09/05/in-which-there-is-silence-and-excuses-for-same/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-05T19:48:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://failcake.github.com/blog/2012/09/05/in-which-there-is-silence-and-excuses-for-same</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello. Where on earth did the last few months go? I guess I could blame it having been
Grand Tour season (the Giro, the Tour and now the Vuelta) which has meant that I've been
watching sweaty men in lycra pedal up the sides of mountains for three weeks at a time.</p>

<p>I guess I can also blame one of those periods when several mildly concerning things
happen in rapid order like a conspiring mob of buses, and when the smoke clears you're
somewhere grim like Burnt Oak, Oldland Common or Quedgeley.</p>

<p>Anyway. Let's see what happens next.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
